Guide to the Journal of Religion Records 1915-1950
University of Chicago Library
Journal of Religion. Records
1915-1950
10.5 linear ft. ( 21 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Journal of Religion Records consist of correspondence from the editorial offices of the Journal of Religion and its two predecessors, The Biblical World and the American Journal of Theology. The correspondence concerns articles and book reviews submitted, subscriptions, budgets and financial matters, and printing arrangements with the University of Chicago Press.
Information on Use
Access
No restrictions.
Historical Note
Founded in 1921, the Journal of Religion was part of a long lineage of religious history and studies journals. One of the journals that the Journal of Religion grew out of was The Biblical World, which in turn was a continuation of a journal founded by William Rainey Harper in 1882. First known as The Hebrew Student, it was re-titled The Old Testament Student and The Old and New Testament Student before becoming The Biblical World in 1893. Harper edited the journal until his death in 1906. The position of editor passed first to Ernest DeWitt Burton, then to Shailer Mathews in 1913. The journal solicited articles on Biblical scholarship, examining historical subjects as well as current religious issues. It was aimed at a popular rather than a strictly academic audience.
Founded in 1897, the American Journal of Theology featured articles of a more technical and scholarly nature than The Biblical World. The title page stated that the "Faculty of the Divinity School" edited the journal, although by 1915 it was acknowledged that most of the faculty members were not directly involved in its production. The journal was reorganized in that year and two managing editors were named, Gerald B. Smith and Shirley Jackson Case, who served through 1920.
The Biblical World and the American Journal of Theology were each published by the Divinity School and managed by a single board of editors. Due to financial difficulties with both publications, it was decided to merge them under a new title, the Journal of Religion, which appeared beginning in 1921 with Gerald Smith as editor. Although intended to combine the features of its two predecessors, the new journal increasingly emphasized the scholarly side of theological studies.
Smith served as editor until 1926, when he was replaced by Shirley J. Case. Upon Case's retirement from the University in 1939, the editorship was given to John Knox (1939
Scope Note
The Journal of Religion Records consist of correspondence from the editorial offices of the Journal of Religion and its two predecessors, The Biblical World and the American Journal of Theology. The correspondence concerns articles and book reviews submitted, subscriptions, budgets and financial matters, and printing arrangements with the University of Chicago Press.
The collection is divided into three series: Series I: The Biblical World Correspondence; Series II: American Journal of Theology Correspondence; and Series III: Journal of Religion Correspondence.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Knox, John, 1900-; McNeill, John Thomas, 1885-; Wilder, Amos Niven, 1895-; Meland, Bernard Eugene, 1899-; Nichols, James Hastings, 1915-; Smith, Gerald Birney, 1868-1929.; Case, Shirley Jackson, 1872-1947; Mathews, Shailer, 1863-1941; Biblical world; Journal of religion; American journal of theology; Theology-Periodicals; Scholarly periodicals
INVENTORY
- Series I: The Biblical World Correspondence
  - 1915, A-B (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1915, C-F (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1915, G-J (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1915, K-L (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1915, M-O (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1915, P-Q (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1915, R-S (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1915, T-Z (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1916, A-B (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1916, C-D (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1916, E-G (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1916, H-L (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1916, M-O (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1916, P-Q (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1916, R-S (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1916, T-Z (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1917 - June 1918, A-B (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1917 - June 1918, C-D (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1917 - June 1918, E-G (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1917 - June 1918, H-J (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1917 - June 1918, K-L (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1917 - June 1918, M-O (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1917 - June 1918, P-Q (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1917 - June 1918, R-S (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1917 - June 1918, T-Z (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - July 1918 - December 1919, A-B (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - July 1918 - December 1919, C-D (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - July 1918 - December 1919, E-G (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - July 1918 - December 1919, H-L (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - July 1918 - December 1919, M-O (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - July 1918 - December 1919, P-Q (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - July 1918 - December 1919, R-S (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - July 1918 - December 1919, T-Z (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1920 - March 1921, A-B (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1920 - March 1921, C-D (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1920 - March 1921, E-G (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1920 - March 1921, H-L (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1920 - March 1921, M-O (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1920 - March 1921, P-R (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1920 - March 1921, S-Z (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series II: American Journal of Theology Correspondence
  - November 1915 - February 1917, A-B (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - November 1915 - February 1917, C-D (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - November 1915 - February 1917, E-G (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - November 1915 - February 1917, H-L (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - November 1915 - February 1917, M-O (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - November 1915 - February 1917, P-Q (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - November 1915 - February 1917, R-S (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - November 1915 - February 1917, T-Z (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - March 1917 - June 1918, A-B (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - March 1917 - June 1918, C-F (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - March 1917 - June 1918, G-L (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - March 1917 - June 1918, M-O (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - March 1917 - June 1918, P-R (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - March 1917 - June 1918, S-Z (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - July 1918 - 1919, A-B (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - July 1918 - 1919, C-F (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - July 1918 - 1919, G-J (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - July 1918 - 1919, K-O (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - July 1918 - 1919, P-Q (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - July 1918 - 1919, R-S (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - July 1918 - 1919, T-Z (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1920 - March 1921, A-B (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 1920 - March 1921, C-F (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 1920 - March 1921, G-L (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - 1920 - March 1921, M-O (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - 1920 - March 1921, P-R (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - 1920 - March 1921, S-Z (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Series III: Journal of Religion Correspondence
  - August 1920 - May 1921, A-B (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - August 1920 - May 1921, C-D (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - August 1920 - May 1921, E-G (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - August 1920 - May 1921, H-J (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - August 1920 - May 1921, K-M (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - August 1920 - May 1921, N-Q (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - August 1920 - May 1921, R-S (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - August 1920 - May 1921, T-Z (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Financial file, 1921-1925 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - June 1921 - June 1922, A-B (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - June 1921 - June 1922, C (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - June 1921 - June 1922, D-G (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - June 1921 - June 1922, H-J (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - June 1921 - June 1922, K-L (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - June 1921 - June 1922, M-O (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - June 1921 - June 1922, P-R (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - June 1921 - June 1922, S (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - June 1921 - June 1922, T-Z (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - July 1922 - October 1923, A-B (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - July 1922 - October 1923, C-D (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - July 1922 - October 1923, E-G (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - July 1922 - October 1923, H-J (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - July 1922 - October 1923, K-L (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - July 1922 - October 1923, M-O (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - July 1922 - October 1923, P-R (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - July 1922 - October 1923, S (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - July 1922 - October 1923, T-Z (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - November 1923 - December 1924, A-B (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - November 1923 - December 1924, C-D (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - November 1923 - December 1924, E-G (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - November 1923 - December 1924, H-J (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - November 1923 - December 1924, K-M (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - November 1923 - December 1924, N-R (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - November 1923 - December 1924, S (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - November 1923 - December 1924, T-Z (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - January - October 1925, A-B (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - January - October 1925, C-F (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - January - October 1925, G-J (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - January - October 1925, K-M (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - January - October 1925, N-R (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - January - October 1925, S (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - January - October 1925, T-Z (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - November 1925 - December 1926, A-B (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - November 1925 - December 1926, C-D (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - November 1925 - December 1926, E-G (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - November 1925 - December 1926, H-L (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - November 1925 - December 1926, M-O (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - November 1925 - December 1926, P-R (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - November 1925 - December 1926, S (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - November 1925 - December 1926, T-Z (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Financial file, 1927-1928 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - January 1927 - February 1928, A-B (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - January 1927 - February 1928, C-D (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - January 1927 - February 1928, E-G (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - January 1927 - February 1928, H-J (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - January 1927 - February 1928, K-L (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - January 1927 - February 1928, M-O (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - January 1927 - February 1928, P-R (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - January 1927 - February 1928, S-Z (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, A (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, B (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, C (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, D (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, E-F (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, G (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, H-J (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, K-L (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, M (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, N-Q (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, R (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, S (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - March 1928 - December 1929, T-Z (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 1930, A-B (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - 1930, C (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - 1930, D (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - 1930, E-F (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - 1930, G-J (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - 1930, K-L (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - 1930, M (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - 1930, N-Q (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - 1930, R-S (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - 1930, T-Z (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - 1931, A-B (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - 1931, C-D (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - 1931, E-G (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - 1931, H-J (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - 1931, K-M (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - 1931, N-R (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - 1931, S (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - 1931, T-Z (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - 1932, A-B (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - 1932, C-D (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - 1932, E-G (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - 1932, H-J (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - 1932, K-M (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - 1932, N-R (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - 1932, S-Z (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - 1933, A-B (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - 1933, C-D (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - 1933, E-J (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - 1933, K-M (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - 1933, N-R (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - 1933, S-Z (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - 1934, A-C (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - 1934, D-J (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - 1934, K-Q (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - 1934, R-S (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - 1934, T-Z (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - 1935, A-C (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - 1935, D-J (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - 1935, K-M (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - 1935, N-R (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - 1935, S-Z (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - 1936, A-C (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - 1936, D-J (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - 1936, K-R (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - 1936, S-Z (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - 1937, A (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - 1937, B (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - 1937, C-D (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - 1937, E-J (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - 1937, K-O (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - 1937, P-R (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - 1937, S-Z (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - 1938, A (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - 1938, B (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - 1938, C-F (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - 1938, G-L (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - 1938, M-O (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - 1938, P-Q (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - 1938, R-S (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - 1938, T-Z (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - 1939, A-C (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - 1939, Case memorial volume (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - 1939, D-F (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - 1939, G (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - 1939, H-L (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - 1939, M-O (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - 1939, P-R (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - 1939, Publishers (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - 1939, S (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - 1939, T-Z (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - 1944-1945, A-B (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - 1944-1945, C (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - 1944-1945, D-F (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - 1944-1945, G-J (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - 1944-1945, K-L (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - 1944-1945, M-O (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - 1944-1945, P-S (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - 1944-1945, T-Z (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - 1946, A-B (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - 1946, C-F (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - 1946, G-J (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - 1946, K-L (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - 1946, M-R (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - 1946, S-Z (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - 1947, A-C (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - 1947, D-G (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - 1947, H-L (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - 1947, M-R (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - 1947, S-Z (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - 1948-1950, A-B (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - 1948-1950, C (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - 1948-1950, Case memorial issue (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - 1948-1950, D-F (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - 1948-1950, G-J (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - 1948-1950, K (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - 1948-1950, L (Box 21, Folder 12)